哦,你好
oh hello
我是Yan
I'm Yan
今天我们要讨论的是
and today we're going to be talking about
计算机架构基础
computer architecture fundamentals
你可能会注意到我在右上角
you might notice I am in the top right corner
而不是一般的右下角
as opposed to the normal lower right corner
是因为这样对幻灯片的干扰更少
that's because I interfere with the slides less that way
抱歉，如果让你感到困惑的话
sorry this confuses you
我们会尽量保持一致，但无法保证
we'll try to be more consistent but no promises
也许有一天我会放在正中间
maybe one day I'll be right in the middle
好吧
all right
我们来谈谈计算机架构
let's talk about computer architecture
这应该只是个回顾
this should be mostly a review for you
在这节课程中
mostly I have this lecture in here
我主要想介绍一个点
to get across a philosophical point
就是计算机架构很酷
that computer architecture is cool
希望你已经在计算机组成原理课程中学习了常规概念
I hope you've learned the general concepts already in a computer organization course
还有汇编语言之类的
along with assembly language and so forth
否则这门课就很难了
cause otherwise this course will be rather difficult
但如果没有
but if not
就启动搜索引擎吧
get warm up Google and
试着跟上
try to follow along
这里我想表达的是
so the point I want to get across in this lecture in some sense is that
条条大路通CPU
all roads lead to the CPU
你可能是一名Python开发人员
you might be a Python developer
你可能喜欢写rust
you might like to write rust
因为你很时髦
because you're very hip
你写的一切
and everything you write
不管它是什么
eventually no matter what it is
最终都是在CPU上执行的二进制指令
ends up being executed as binary encoder instructions on a CPU
如果你写的是RUST
right if you're writing rust
会有一个编译器
you have a compiler
它会编译你的代码
that compiles your code
然后变成在CPU上运行的二进制代码
and then that becomes a binary code running on the CPU
如果你运行的是Python
if you're running Python
会有个解释器
you might have an interpreter
它是一个在CPU上执行的二进制程序
that is a binary program executing on the CPU
执行你代码想要做的事情
performing the things that your code wants to do
你可能会说，等等，Yan
you might say but wait Yan
我用的pypy——Python的实时编译器
I use pypy a just in time compiler for Python
或者我用的Javascript之类的东西
or I use Javascript or something along those lines
那么你的代码就不是被解释的了
then your code isn't interpreted
它会在执行时编译成二进制指令
it is compiled on the fly into binary instructions
最终在你的CPU上执行
that end up getting executed on your CPU
一个例外是像Cuda这样的语言
one potential exception to this is languages like Cuda
你的代码也会被编译成二进制指令
that where you write code that ends up as binary compiled instructions
但会在GPU上执行
that get executed on a GPU
但在介绍计算机模型时，GPU和CPU都差不多
but a GPU and a CPU for this purpose are basically the same thing
我们来深入到CPU
let's drill down into the CPU
这个真的很底层
whoa that's really far down
这个深度
so this is basically as deep down into a CPU
对于计科人很合适了
as is reasonable to drill for a computer scientist
这些是逻辑门
right these are logic gates
从概念上讲
conceptually speaking
你的CPU里有很多很多逻辑门在疯狂计算
at the center of your CPU are many many many logic gates computing furiously
以为你呈现出这个视频
to bring you this lecture
或者解决你的其它需求
or whatever else you use your computer for
我个人认为
personally I think that
我们应该从逻辑门开始计算机科学教育
logic gates is where we should start computer science education
现在
right now
我们都从表层的Python啊、Java啊开始
we start on a high level with Python and Java
If语句、for循环
if statements and for loops
这都是逻辑门的内容
it's all about logic gates right
如果我们从逻辑门开始
so if we started with logic gates
然后我们就能建立概念认知
and then we built up the concepts
我认为这能让
I think it would make for a much more
计算机科学教育更循序渐进
smooth step by step computer science education
因为逻辑门的概念非常简单
because the concept of a logic gate is very simple
有大概四种类型的逻辑门
there are let's say four types of logic gates
但你可以构造出
but you can really build
相当多
quite a lot
你可以用任意三个逻辑门来构建其他逻辑门
you can build the other logic gates using any three
有与门
there's the and gate
与门有两个输入
you have two inputs to your and gate
如果两者都为真
if both of them are true
输出为真
the output is true
'真' 是什么意思?
what does true mean
根据物理介质的不同，“真”的含义也不同
well true means different things depending on the physical medium
如果是内部用电的计算机
if you have a computer that runs on electricity internally
你的输入
then you have your inputs
“真”或“不真”的界限是一个电压阈值
true or not true is some sort of a voltage threshold
如果两条线都有电压进来
so if there's some voltage coming in on both wires
那么与门会有个电压输出
there will be a voltage coming out for an and gate
如果你有某种光学门
if you have some sort of an optical gate those exist
介质就是光
it can be light
看有光进来吗
is light coming in
也可以是水
you could have water
你可以用杯子造一个与门
you can build an and gate out of a cup
由水和重力驱动
powered by water and gravity
至少能造一个 或门
an or gate out of a cup at least
如果你在杯子底部钻一个洞
if you drill a hole in the bottom of the cup
杯子上面接入两根水管
you have two pipes going into the cup
如果其中一个管子有水
if either pipe has water
水就会从杯子底部流出来
there will be water pouring out of that cup
或门 有两个输入一个输出
so an or gate two inputs one output
有一个输入为真，则输出为真
either the inputs is true the output is true
你可以在电子游戏中构建这些逻辑门
you could build these things in video games
也的确有人这么做
and people do
有人在游戏中构建一整个计算机
people build whole computers in video games
如果你玩矮人要塞
if you play Dwarf Fortress
你可能遇到过
you've likely encountered
有人讨论他们用
people talking about computers that they built
水做计算介质制造的计算机
using water as the computing medium
他们用水或其他的构建逻辑门
so they build logic gates on water and so forth
在我的世界里，你可以使用红石
in Minecraft you can use Redstone
有很多不同的方法可以做到这一点
and there's tons and tons of different ways to do it
异或门有2个输入
you have XOR gates where you have two inputs
只有一个输入为真，则输出为真
and if only one of those inputs is true the output is true
如果2个都为真，则输出为假
if they're both true the output is false
如果都为假，则输出为假
if they're both false the output is false
还有 非门
and then of course you have not gates
如果输入为真
where if the input is true
只有一个输入
your one input
输出为假
the output is also is false
如果输入为假，输出为真
and if the input is false the output is true
这很简单
this is very simple
这是一个非常简单的概念
it's a trivially simple concept
如果你学过离散数学
if you've taken discrete mathematics
你可能已经围绕这个创建了真值表
you've probably created truth tables around this
这很直观
and it's just it's very straightforward
有趣的是，通过巧妙地组合这些门
and the interesting thing is by combining these gates in clever ways
我们可以一步一步创建出计算器
we can start taking small steps to a computer
像这样
like this
这张幻灯片上有很多不同的门的组合
all right so this slide has a bunch of different combinations of gates
这张幻灯片上有一个加法器
there's an adder on this slide
如果你给它两个数字
where basically if you give it two numbers
以及之前计算留下的进位标志
and a carry flag from previous computation
它会给你加法的结果
and it'll give you a result of the addition
当然还有一个进位标志
and a carry flag of course
这里的数字还很小
in this case the numbers are simple bits
但能做出支持任意大的数字的加法器
but you can make adders that work on arbitrarily large
只要你有更多的门
you know as long as you have more and more gates
更多的输入
and larger and larger inputs
还有个多路选择器
there's a multiplexer there where you can
可以根据你的输入
based on your input
选择一个输出信号
you can select one of the signals one output signal
例如，这在内存中起到了明显作用
that for example has obvious implications for memory
如果你想读取计算机内存
where if you want to read some memory in a computer
或者查询python数组
or seek into your python array
某些时候，类似的决策，是由这种门组合做出的
at some point some decision like this gets made on logic gates
这很令人兴奋
which is pretty exciting
说到内存
speaking of memory
内存也是由ppt上的这些逻辑门做出的
there's also memory made out of logic gates on this slide
所以你能巧妙地组合逻辑门
so you can use a clever combination of logic gates
来存储、读取
to be able to store read and
存储和读取内存
store and read memory
这里是单独一位内存
single bits of memory right here right
基本上这些组合以及潜力是无尽的
basically the combinations and the potential is endless
在某个神奇的临界点
and at some point some incredibly magical point
我们能从简单的逻辑门组合
we move from just some logic gates that are super simple
能直接写纸上
you can write them out on the paper
完全没什么特殊的
there's nothing special about them
从杯子上扣洞就能创建的或门
you can drill a hole in the cup and have an or gate
进化到计算机
to a computer
计算机有其神奇之处
there's some magical thing to a computer
计算机可以计算
a computer can compute
单个逻辑门不能进行真正的计算
a logic gate can't really compute
现在我们穿过这个临界点
so now we've crossed this magical threshold
到达另一边
and then right on the other side
本课程大多操作的，临界点上的二进制级别
this threshold is where much of this course will operate on the binary level
还有该级别上的安全问题
and security issues and implications there
这也是我喜欢计算机的地方
that's the part I love about computing
这个神奇的边界就是计算开始发生的地方
this magical boundary where computing starts to happen
现代计算机抽象出来，看着大概像这样
a modern computer might look something like this at a very high level
有CPU
you have your CPU
它通过某种硬件桥，采用某种通信协议，连接
it communicates over some sort of a hardware bridge or whatever protocol
到内存
to memory
到硬盘
to your disk
到网络
to your network
到你的显示器，等等
to your monitor etc etc etc right
让我们把重点放在内存、磁盘、网络等方面
so let's focus on memory disk network and so forth
再深入些
and drill just a little deeper
CPU不是一个单独东西
your CPU isn't just a monolithic thing
它有不同的组成部分
it has parts like different different components
它有寄存器
it has registers
可以与之交互的小块内存
small bits of memory that it can interact with
准确说是一些小的存储空间
or sort of small bits of storage
不要和主存储器（内存）搞混了
not to get confused with the main memory
它有一个控制单元
it has a control unit
这个控制单元决定执行什么
this control unit decides what to execute
解码指令
decodes instructions
并将事情分派给CPU的其他部分
and dispatches things due to other parts of the CPU
CPU还有一个算术逻辑单元
and the computer has an Arithmetic Logic Unit right
各种计算、加法之类的，发生在这里
where the various computations adding and so forth happens
还有其他部分
and there are other parts
浮点处理器
there's floating point processors
计算机有各种各样的部件
there's all sorts of parts of a computer at a high level
在此基础上
let's stick with this
再加个东西
and add one thing
CPU缓存
there's a caching
实际上
turns out
现代计算机体系结构基本上是一系列缓存层
that modern computer architecture is basically a series of caching layers
叠在一起
stacked on top of each other
一开始
so you start out
你可以想到一个最大的
you can think of the biggest biggest possible one
就是互联网
and it's the internet
互联网的存储空间大得惊人
right the internet has insane amounts of storage
很大的存储空间
storage that you could never hope to
如此多的数据，你没法将其全部放在一处
so much data that you can never hope to acquire it all in one location
还有一层是硬盘
and at one location that you have of course is a disk
这里可以存储大量数据
where you can put a lot of data
超过了你电脑内存的容量
more than could fit into your computer's memory
你正在使用的东西就在内存中
which is what you want just the stuff that you are actively working on to be in
如果你在玩游戏
if you are actively playing a game
你想把尽可能多的游戏数据放到内存中
you want as much of that as possible to be in memory
而不是一直与硬盘交换内存页
rather than swapping in and out of disk
因为硬盘访问速度很慢
because disk access is slow
随着我们向上走，存储空间变得越来越小
as we move up and get smaller and smaller on these storage sizes
速度越来越快
the trend is we get faster and faster
所以，网络访问速度慢
so accessing network is slow
你必须将数据包发到世界各地
you have to send packets across the world
访问硬盘要快得多
accessing your disk is much faster but
访问内存的速度比这还要快
accessing memory is even faster than that
从内存读取出的数据
when you read from memory
会进入CPU的一个特殊位置
it goes into a special place in your CPU
叫CPU缓存
that special place called the cache
你从里面读数据
you read from that
往里面放数据
you move it to the cache and then
这比访问内存快，但小得多
that is faster than memory but much much smaller
然后CPU从缓存中提取数据
and then the CPU pulls from the cache
存入寄存器
to put data into registers
它们的速度极快
and those are extraordinarily fast
但很小很贵
but so small so expensive
具体取决于哪种架构
that there's very depending on the architecture
大概有8到40个
anywhere from like 8 to 40 of them but you know
大小为2到8字节，甚至有的有16字节
and they're anywhere from 2 to 8 bytes to maybe 16 bytes sometimes in size
所以它
so it's
越来越快
you're getting gradually faster and faster
但是越来越小
but gradually smaller and smaller
然后
and then
你的CPU实际只操作缓存和寄存器
your CPU actually acts only on your cache and your registers
其他的都会加载到或加载出它们
everything else gets loaded in and out of it
计算机体系结构很有趣
it's a very interesting computer architecture
近年来变得更复杂了些
in recent years has gotten complicated a little bit more
我们的CPU有了多核
in that our CPUs actually have multiple cores
如果你有一个多核处理器
so if you have a multi core processor
基本大家都有
which basically more or less everybody at this point does
你可能有多个核
you likely have multiple cores
每个核都有自己的缓存，自己的寄存器，等等
each of them has its own cache its own registers etc etc
然后不同核共享一个缓存
and then they share a common cache
然后再是内存、硬盘、网络
and then you have memory disk network and so on
这个计算机架构从何而来
where did we get this computer architecture
它出自这3位约翰
well we got it from these 3 Johns
一个物理学家，一个电气工程师和一个数学家
a physicist an electrical engineer and a mathematician
创造了后来被称为
created what ended up being called
因为冯诺依曼单独署名的草案（First Draft ... EDVAC）
due to a misadventure with a draft
被称为冯·诺伊曼架构
the von Neumann Architecture
它是莫切利和埃克特写的论文的草案
draft of a paper that John Mauchly and John Eckert were writing
所以冯·诺伊曼架构是
so the von Neumann Architecture is
一系列逐渐变小但加快的缓存层
this series of shrinking but increasing in speed layers
最终
where in the end
有趣的是
we have something very interesting in that
CPU工作在缓存和寄存器等部件时
the CPU as it works on its cache and registers and so forth
在很大程度上
for the most part
不区分数据与代码
doesn't differentiate between data code and etc right
我们以后再探索它的含义
this has implications that we'll explore later
在后面的模块
in later modules
但我想先介绍一下这个背景
but I wanted to give you this background
为以后打下基础
to set the stage for the future of this course
我希望你们和我一样喜欢这个话题
I hope that you enjoyed this topic as much as I enjoy it
这是当教授的好处之一
one of the nice perks of being a professor
是能或多或少地讲你想讲的东西
is being able to lecture more or less about whatever you want
这是我对这门课的补充
so this was my addition to the course
我们会在以后的视频中再见
otherwise I will see you or you will see me in future videos
谢谢
thanks